原视频名：How Do Starlink Satellites Navigate To Their Final Operational Orbits
原作者名：Scott Manley
视频来源：youtu.be/VIQr1UyhwWk
原视频发布日期：20210803
字幕翻译：WJIJKKH，校对：旋火
Hello it's Scott Manley here.
你好 我是Scott Manley
Over the last two years we've seen about 30 Starlink launches
在过去的两年里 我们已经看到了大约30次星链的发射
carrying a total of over 1700 satellites into low earth orbit
这些任务携带了总共超过1700颗卫星进入低地球轨道
and by the end of June
而到了6月底
SpaceX had finished launching all the satellites required to bring the Starlink constellation to full functionality
SpaceX已经发射了使星链星座实现完整功能所需的所有卫星
but users of Starlink aren't getting full functionality from the network just yet
但星链的用户还没有从星链网络中获得其全部的功能
because it actually takes a few months for Starlink satellites
因为星链卫星实际上需要几个月的时间
to go from their initial injection orbits to their final orbit
从最初的射入轨道达到最终的轨道
and I kind of want to talk about this whole process
而我想谈一谈这整个过程
because it's kind of fascinating the different tricks they use to distribute the satellites into their final orbits
因为他们将卫星分配到它们的最终轨道上所用的技巧
and how these final orbits are arranged.
以及这些最终轨道是如何安排的 有些迷人
So this is the orbit viewer from celestrak.com
所以这是来自celestrak网的轨道查看器
and every single dot here represents a Starlink satellite.
并且这里的每一个点都代表一颗星链卫星
Now most of these are in their final orbits
现在 这些卫星中的大多数都在其最终轨道上
and if you look at them you can sort of see these vertical lines running up and down
并且如果你看一下它们 你可以看到这些垂直线在上下移动
and they more or less alternate with one group going up
而且它们或多或少地交替出现 一组往上走
and then an adjacent group going down and so on and so forth
然后相邻的一组往下走 如此反复
and you might be inclined to think of these sort of regular spacings as orbital planes
而你可能倾向于认为这些有规律的间隔是轨道平面
but actually the orbits are all moving on a 53 degree inclination
但实际上这些轨道都是在以53度的倾角运动的
so now you can see this one Starlink satellite selected
所以现在你可以看到这个被选中的星链卫星
and if you look on that green line
并且如果你看那条绿线
you can see another one which is just crossing the coast of Africa
你可以看到另一颗卫星正在穿越非洲的海岸线
and there's another one coming up
而且还有一个即将到来
so these inclined angles those represent the different orbital planes
所以这些角度倾斜的线条代表了不同的轨道平面
and it becomes much more obvious when I use this diagram
并且当我使用这个图时 它变得更加明显了
which I created using a script of my own and some python.
这是我用自己的脚本和一些python代码创建的
And what you're seeing here is the lines showing the orbits
并且你在这里看到的是表示轨道的线条
and they are changing over time in this case.
而在这种情况下 它们是随时间变化的
In this diagram by the way the camera is fixed.
顺便一说 在这张图中 摄像机位是固定的
What we're actually doing is we're running times time forward.
我们实际上在做的是让时间向前运行
You'll notice that we're doing like a couple of days every second.
你会注意到 我们一秒钟就代表好几天
Well these orbits are being pulled around by earth's equatorial bulge right.
这些轨道被地球的赤道隆起所拉动 对吗
胖地球理论指的是，由于地球赤道隆起(地球质量不均匀)造成的引力变动，卫星轨道会随时间流逝而进动
Scott Manley于2018年6月6日视频中创造的词，玩梗地平说(Flat Earth Theory)，出处youtu.be/UCMSDvp-n74
Again this is Fat Earth Theory.
这又是胖地球理论
At Starlink's operational altitude
在星链的工作高度上
the earth shape causes the orbits to precess around at a rate of about four and a half degrees per day
地球的形状导致其轨道以每天约4.5度的速度进动
so when it's fully deployed we expect to have 72 orbital planes
所以当它完全部署后 我们预计会有72个轨道平面
with each of them separated by five degrees at the equator
每个轨道平面在赤道上相隔5度
and each plane will contain about 22 satellites distributed are around the orbit
并且每个轨道平面将包含大约22颗卫星 分布在轨道上
and so this diagram from Starlink.sx
所以这个来自Starlink.sx的图表
gives you a better idea of what the situation is with regard to the planes.
可以让你更好地了解关于这些轨道平面的情况
What we've got now is we've changed the coordinates up.
我们现在有的是 我们已经改变了坐标
Along the bottom you have the angle relative to like a start point
沿着底部 你有一个相对于起始点的角度(升交点经度)
where the orbit plane crosses the equator.
起始点也就是轨道平面穿过赤道的地方
And the second one the vertical axis
而第二个是纵轴
is how far along that the satellite is at a specific time.
是卫星在一定时间内所运行的距离
So you see these nice vertical lines with  about 20 satellites in each of these planes
所以你可以看到这些漂亮的垂直线 每条垂直线上有大约20颗卫星
and then there's a few which are missing right now.
然后现在还有一些卫星没有出现在图中
So generally the Starlink launches have carried about 60 satellites.
因此一般来说 星链的每次发射会携带大约60颗卫星
Some have carried fewer because they have Rideshare
有些发射中携带的星链卫星数量会较少 因为有别的卫星搭顺车
but the way they're deployed is in one big batch.
但它们的部署方式是一次大批量部署
In fact the whole spacecraft just rotates around horizontally
事实上 整个航天器只是在水平方向上旋转
and at one point they just let the clamps go
而在某个时刻 他们只是让夹子释放
and these things fly off like sort of scattering a pack of cards around the room.
然后这些东西就飞走了 就像在房间里散开一包纸牌一样
They're not coordinated.
它们之间并不协调
They're not carefully ejected like you see with the other satellite constellations.
它们没有像你在其他卫星星座部署中看到的那样被小心地弹出
The satellites bump up against each other.
这些卫星相互碰撞
They come out with random speeds
它们以随机的速度被部署
and then from there they have the job of getting to their final orbit.
然后从那里开始 它们的工作就是要到达其最终轨道
So yeah the satellites themselves are about 260 kilograms in mass.
所以 是的 星链卫星本身的质量约为260公斤
They're flat packed.
它们是以扁平的形状打包的
They have solar panels.
它们有太阳能电池板
They have all the antenna.
它们有各种的天线
They have a little ion engine in there, a Hall-effect thruster fueled by krypton gas.
它们有一个小的离子引擎 也就是一个以氪气为燃料的霍尔效应推进器
And I find the decision to use krypton.
而且我发现推进剂使用氪气的决定
A fascinating example of how SpaceX has tried to make these things as low cost as affordable as possible.
是SpaceX尝试尽可能降低这些东西成本的一个非凡例子
Normally with a Hall-effect thruster you would use xenon gas
通常 对于霍尔效应推进器 你会使用氙气
because for the same amount of electrical power you are going to get much more thrust.
因为对于消耗同样的电力 你将得到更大的推力
But you're also going to pay more than 10 times the price to get xenon over krypton
但是 你也将支付超过氪气10倍的价格来获得氙气
and in fact when you're talking about tens of thousands of satellites
并且事实上 当你在谈论数以万计的卫星时
that's a serious part of the world market for xenons
那是世界氙气市场的一个重要部分
who would probably push the price even higher if they wanted to do that.
如果他们想这样做 他们可能会把氙气的价格推得更高
So the fact that they're working with krypton is critical.
因此 对氪的使用是至关重要的
Anyway those thrusters will be very important in bringing the satellites up to their final orbit
总之 这些推进器对于将卫星带入其最终轨道非常重要
but there's other tricks that they have to use
但他们还必须使用其他的技巧
to make sure that they get separated into their different orbital planes.
以确保卫星被分离到不同的轨道平面
so first thing is as soon as they're released they're all sort of randomly floating there in space
所以第一件事是 当它们被释放时 它们都是随机地漂浮在太空中的
and as they go orbit they will get spread out just due to having slightly different orbits
而当它们进入轨道时 会被分散开来 只因为它们的轨道略有不同
and there's a bit of randomization that goes on in the sort of chaotic deployment process.
并且在这种混乱的部署过程中会有一些随机性的变化
It actually takes them a while to figure out which one is which
实际上 他们需要一段时间来弄清楚哪一个卫星是哪一个
so that they can start giving them commands
这样他们才可以开始给它们发送指令
in the certainty that they aren't going to crash into each other
以确定 在当它们开始展开它们的天线并试图移动时
when they start unfolding their antenna and trying to move.
它们不会互相碰撞
Now once the engines start up and the satellites begin to maneuver
现在 一旦发动机启动 并且卫星开始机动
the first thing they do is raise their orbits from the initial insertion orbit
它们做的第一件事 就是把它们的轨道从最初的入轨轨道进行提升
which is below 300 kilometers.
入轨轨道也就是高度低于300公里的轨道
And bring them to a sort of temporary parking orbit between about 350 400 kilometers
并把轨道提升到大约在350到400公里之间的一种临时停泊轨道上
and they will spend some time there
而它们将在那里度过一些时间
before then finally boosting up to about 550 kilometers which is their final operational orbit.
然后再最终将轨道提升到大约550公里处 也就是它们的最终运行轨道
And satellites from the same launch will spend different amounts of time in that temporary parking orbit
并且同一次发射的卫星将在临时停泊轨道上停留不同的时间
before proceeding to their final operational orbit.
然后再进入其最终运行轨道
Some will go straight there.
有些卫星会直接进入那里
Typically about 20 from each launch of 60.
一般来说 这样的卫星在每次发射的60颗卫星中大约有20颗
Then the ones that remain in the lower orbit
然后那些留在较低轨道上的卫星
because they are closer to the earth
因为它们离地球更近
they get bigger effects due to the oblateness of the earth and their orbits twist around faster
它们会受到地球扁率更大的影响 并且其轨道进动得更快
so you can see this the lower orbit is getting pulled around faster
所以你可以看到 低轨道被拉动的速度更快
and therefore it is being split into separate planes
因此 它被分离到了不同的轨道平面
by choosing when they want to fire their engines to bring them up to their operational orbit.
通过选择它们想要启动发动机的时间 可以把它们带到(不同的)运行轨道上
So this is how you get multiple satellites from a single launch into different orbital planes.
所以这就是你如何使一次发射中的多颗卫星进入不同的轨道平面
Normally orbital plane changes are very expensive in terms of propellant.
通常情况下 轨道平面变化所消耗的推进剂是非常昂贵的
To go from one plane to the next takes about 500 meters per second of delta v at these altitudes.
在这些高度上 从一个平面到下一个平面上需要大约500米每秒的DV(速度增量)
To raise the orbit takes about 170
而提升轨道需要大约170米每秒的DV
so this is three times more expensive to do this using propellant
所以在使用推进剂的情况下 改变轨道平面花费的量 是提升轨道的三倍
but if you can use the earth's gravity and you can afford to wait that amount of time
但如果你能利用地球的引力 并且你能等得起这么长的时间
then you can do it more efficiently.
那么你就可以节约地做到这一点
Another thing to notice by the way there's some rogue objects which after going up
还有一点要注意的是 有一些反常的物体在上升之后
they start to fall back down into lower orbits.
会开始回落到较低的轨道上
Those are sometimes satellites which have had some problem
那些有时是一些出现了问题的卫星
and they're bringing them back down to either test them or sometimes dispose of them in the atmosphere.
而他们会把它们的轨道降低 来测试它们或者让它们坠入大气层销毁
And over the last two years of Starlink deployment
并且在过去两年的星链部署中
they've disposed of about five percent of their satellites
他们已经丢弃了大约百分之五的卫星
so this is like a whole animation showing all the launches and finishing in June of this year.
现在展示的这整个动画 显示了直到今年6月结束以来的所有发射
This is the very first batch that was launched in 2019.
这是在2019年发射的第一批星链卫星
Most of these are no longer operational.
其中大部分已不再运作
They were not the final version.
它们不是星链卫星的最终版本
They didn't have the same capabilities.
它们没有与最终版本相同的能力
But you see now in 2020 they really start launching these in large amounts.
但你现在可以看到 在2020年他们真正开始大量发射这些卫星
Also note that the orbits are supposed to be somewhat color-coded.
还要注意的是 轨道应该是有一些颜色标记的
They're supposed to be red when they're close to the earth
当它们接近地球时 它们的轨道应该是红色的
and green when they're in their final orbit.
而当它们进入最终轨道时其轨道为绿色
The active number here is totally a guess.
这里的正常运作卫星的数字完全是一种猜测
I didn't actually have anything beyond taking their altitude and saying that they were above 500 kilometers
我实际上没有任何其他佐证资料 我只知道它们的高度在500公里以上
so that's not a perfect number but it's a pretty good estimate.
所以这不是一个完美的数字 但它是一个相当好的估计
And again I have to make it clear that I've exaggerated the height differences here
并且我必须再次说明 我已经夸大了这里的高度差异
so you can see the orbit raising and lowering.
所以你可以看到轨道的上升和下降
In reality the earth is like 6400 kilometers in radius
现实中 地球的半径大约是6400公里
and the satellites don't get 600 kilometers above the surface
而这些卫星离地表不到600公里
so it would be like 10 percent of this radius in real life.
所以在现实中 它们的轨道高度将是地球半径的百分之十
It's also worth noting the satellites that are in polar orbit from the Rideshare missions.
还值得注意的是 搭车任务中处于极地轨道的卫星
Those do the same thing.
那些卫星会做同样的事情
They end up spreading themselves around.
它们最终会让自己扩散到周围
So if you look at all the satellites from a typical launch
因此 如果你观察来自一次标准发射中的所有星链卫星
this is what the height versus time graph.
现在这里显示的是高度与时间的关系图
again thanks to Jonathan Mcdowell who's been tracking this.
再次感谢一直在跟踪这个的Jonathan Mcdowell
He's a great person to follow for all satellite operations.
他是跟踪所有卫星运行的一个伟大人物
So you can see the satellites going up to their 380 kilometer mark
所以你可以看到卫星升到了380公里的高度位置
and then they sit there.
然后它们停留在那里
Some of them go straight to their final orbit.
它们中的一些卫星直接进入了其最终轨道
Some of them wait a while and go up to different orbital planes
它们中的另一些卫星等待了一段时间 并上升到不同的轨道平面
But now as the orbits have been getting filled in with about 20 from each launch
但是现在 由于轨道已经被来自每次发射中的大约20颗卫星填满
the later launchers have had to spend more time moving their satellites around to hit the planes that they want
后面的发射者必须花更多时间来移动其卫星 以达到其目标的轨道平面
and possibly just have single satellites go up to fill in gaps
并且也可能只是让单颗卫星升空来填补缺口
that have been found or resulted from failed satellites.
这些缺口可能是被发现的 或是因卫星故障而产生的
Now that covers separation of the satellites into their different orbital planes
那么 这包括将卫星分离到它们不同的轨道平面上
but moving or distributing the satellites along a specific orbital plane uniformly
但是 沿着一个特定的轨道平面均匀地移动或分配卫星
that's interesting to look at as well.
那也是一个有趣的问题
So this is an animation by Elias Eccli I found it posted on the NASASpaceflight forums.
所以 这是我在NASA航天论坛上发现的一个由Elias Eccli制作的动画
So again along the horizontal axis
所以再次沿着横轴看
you've got the longitude of the ascending node
你在这里有升交点经度
which is pretty much where the satellites cross the equator relative to the starts
其差不多是卫星经过赤道的位置 相对于经度原点(春分点)的角度
and on the vertical axis you've got the angle along the orbit
而在纵轴上 则是轨道近点角(anomaly)
and one important thing is that these are at different altitudes.
并且有一件重要的事是 这些都是在不同的高度上
Now there is an altitude scale on the right here
那么 这里的右边有一个高度刻度
but it's actually just easier to look and see that
但实际上 更容易观察高度的是
the ones moving fast downwards are in lower orbits
图中快速向下移动的物体是在较低的轨道上的
because this is relative to the target parking orbit.
因为这张图是相对于目标停泊轨道而绘制的
So what we see here is we've got one group
所以我们在这里看到的是 我们有一组卫星
that are more or less now fixed and distributed along their orbit
它们或多或少现在是固定的 并沿其轨道分布的
but they start out in their parking orbits in a tight little bundle
但它们在停泊轨道上开始时是紧密的一小堆
and only when they begin to raise their orbit do they begin to spread out towards their target orbit
而只有当它们开始提升其轨道时 它们才开始向其目标轨道散开
and then very carefully move until they reach their final location.
然后非常小心地移动 直到它们到达最后的位置
So the fact that these ones remain very close together during this parking time.
因此事实是 在这个停留时间内 这些这些卫星离彼此非常近
That is intentional.
那是故意的
That couldn't happen by accident.
这不可能是偶然发生的
If they were uncontrolled they would spread out much more rapidly.
如果它们不受控制 它们会更快地散开
So I don't know why they do this.
所以我不知道他们为什么要这样做
Maybe it makes it easier for them to control them or check them out
也许这使他们更容易控制或检查它们
or just it makes the math easier
或者只是让数学运算更容易
but yeah this is how they end up getting moved into their final distribution along the orbits.
但是 是的 这就是他们如何将卫星沿轨道移动到其最终分布位置的
If you look carefully you can also see a few objects which are moving upwards
如果你仔细观察动画 你还可以看到一些正在向上移动的物体
and those ones are in higher orbits
而这些物体在更高的轨道上
and so again because of Fat Earth Theory they are processing relative to the others
并且因此 同样由于胖地球理论 它们相对于其他物体会逐渐进动
but they're doing it more slowly
但它们进行得更慢
so those are ones which took a little longer to reach the final operational orbit
所以这些物体花了更多的时间来达到其最终的运行轨道
and because of that they have moved a little too far westwards
也正因为如此 它们向西移动得有点远了
so by moving into a higher orbit they move eastwards until they get in line with all the others.
因此 通过进入更高的轨道 它们向东移动 直到与其他所有的轨道一致
And then they can finally take their spot in the formation.
然后他们终于可以在编队中占据自己的位置
SpaceX aren't the only company launching a mega constellation for communication.
SpaceX并不是唯一为了通讯而发射大型卫星星座的公司
OneWeb is also doing this and they do pretty much similar things.
OneWeb也在做这个 并且他们做的事情基本相似
They launch to initial higher orbits.
他们将卫星发射到较高的初始轨道
They use the Soyuz and they have fewer satellites per launch
他们使用联盟号 并且他们每次发射的卫星数量较少
but they also have much higher operational orbits
但他们也有更高的运行轨道
so it takes them a fair amount of time to reach out to those as well.
所以他们也需要相当多的时间来达到这些轨道
OneWeb are of course still in the process of launching their constellation.
当然 OneWeb公司仍在发射其卫星星座
The final constellation should have over 600 satellites in it
最终的卫星星座系统里应该有超过600颗卫星
and they've launched about one third of that.
而他们已经发射了其中的三分之一
They don't need as many satellites as Starlink because they are at higher orbits
他们不需要像星链那样多的卫星 因为他们的卫星在更高的轨道上
and therefore each satellite can see a much larger area of the earth.
因此 每颗卫星可以覆盖到地球上更大的区域
So anyway I hope you see now that it's not just about launching satellites into orbit
因此无论如何 我希望你现在能知道 这不只是将卫星发射到轨道上
but the subsequent delicate dance of orbital mechanics
而还有随后的轨道力学微妙的作用
that puts the satellites in the locations in the orbits where they need to be to perform their job.
二者一同 把卫星送到了它们需要工作的轨道位置上
I'm Scott Manley. Fly safe.
我是Scott Manley 切记 注意飞行安全
[Music]
[音乐]